One thing I wanted to say about film making is -- about this film --
أحد الأشياء التي أردت قولها عن صناعة الأفلام - و عن هذا الفلم بالأخص-
in thinking about some of the wonderful talks we've heard here,
هي أنني و بالنظر إلى بعض أروع المحاضرات التي سمعناها هنا،
Michael Moschen, and some of the talks about music,
مايكل موشين، و بعض المحاضرات عن الموسيقى،
this idea that there is a narrative line,
و مع فكرة أن هناك خطاً قصصياً ورائها،
and that music exists in time.
و بأن الموسيقى جزء من "الزمن".
A film also exists in time; it's an experience
الفلم أيضاً جزء من "الزمن"، إنه تجربة
that you should go through emotionally.
يجب عليك أن تمر بها عاطفياً.
And in making this film I felt that so many of the documentaries I've seen
و خلال صنعي لهذا الفلم أحسست بأن العديد من الأفلام الوثائقية التي شاهدتها
were all about learning something,
كانت تدور حول تعلم شيء ما،
or knowledge, or driven by talking heads, and driven by ideas.
أو تدور حول المعرفة، أو أنها نتاج مفكرين و أفكار جديدة و رائعة.
And I wanted this film to be driven by emotions,
و لكنني أردت لهذا الفلم أن يكون مقاداً بالعواطف لا بالأفكار
and really to follow my journey.
و يتبع مسيرتي بحق.
So instead of doing the talking head thing, instead it's composed of scenes,
و لذلك بدلاً من مقابلة بعض الأشخاص، قمت بتشكيل الفلم من مشاهد لأماكن
and we meet people along the way.
التقينا فيها أناساً على طول الطريق.
We only meet them once.
نلتقيهم مرة واحدة فقط.
They don't come back several times, so it really chronicles a journey.
و هؤلاء الناس لا يعودون عدة مرات، إنه بحق تسجيل لأحداث الرحلة.
It's something like life, that once you get in it
إنه شيء أشبه بالحياة، ما إن تدخلها
you can't get out.
لا تستطيع الخروج منها.
There are two clips I want to show you,
أريد أن أعرض عليكم مقطعين،
the first one is a kind of hodgepodge,
الأول عبارة عن خليط
its just three little moments, four little moments
عبارة عن بضع لحظات
with three of the people who are here tonight.
مع ثلاثة من الأشخاص المتواجدين هنا اليوم.
It's not the way they occur in the film,
و ليس المهم في هذه المقاطع كيفية وقوعها في الفلم
because they are part of much larger scenes.
لأنها جزء من مشاهد أكبر.
They play off each other in a wonderful way.
و تتفاعل هذه المشاهد و الأحداث بشكل رائع مع بعضها البعض.
And that ends with a little clip of my father, of Lou,
و تنتهي هذه المشاهد بمقطع صغير لوالدي
talking about something that is very dear to him,
متحدثاً عن شيء عزيز جداً إلى نفسه
which is the accidents of life.
و هو حوادث الحياة و أحداثها.
I think he felt that the greatest things in life were accidental,
أعتقد أنه كان يشعر بأن أعظم الأشياء في الحياة هي الأشياء العرضية
and perhaps not planned at all.
و الأشياء الغير مخططة على الإطلاق.
And those three clips will be followed by a scene of
و هذه المقاطع الثلاث ستتبع بمشهد
perhaps what, to me, is really his greatest building
لأحد أروع الأبنية - بنظري - التي صممها
which is a building in Dhaka, Bangladesh.
و الموجود في دكا - نبغلاديش.
He built the capital over there.
لقد بنى البرلمان هنا
And I think you'll enjoy this building, it's never been seen --
و أعتقد أنكم ستعجبون بهذا المبنى الذي لم يرى من قبل
it's been still photographed, but never photographed by a film crew.
تم تصوير هذا المبنى بصور ثابتة و لكن لم يتم تصويره بكاميرا فيديو من قبل
We were the first film crew in there.
و كنا نحن أول فريق تصوير هناك.
So you'll see images of this remarkable building.
سترون صوراً لهذا المبنى المميز
A couple of things to keep in mind when you see it,
و عليكم أن تأخذوا بضع أشياء بعين الاعتبار عند مشاهدته
it was built entirely by hand,
الأول : أنه بني بالكامل يدوياً
I think they got a crane the last year.
أعتقد أنهم أحضروا رافعة العام السابق
It was built entirely by hand off bamboo scaffolding,
تم بناؤه يدوياً و باستخدام سقالات خشب البامبو
people carrying these baskets of concrete on their heads,
كان الناس يحملون سلال الاسمنت على رؤوسهم
dumping them in the forms.
و يقومون بافراغها في المستوعبات والقوالب.
It is the capital of the country,
إنه مركز البلد و مركز الديمقراطية فيه
and it took 23 years to build,
و استغرق 23 سنة لبنائه
which is something they seem to be very proud of over there.
و هو ما يبدو أنهم فخورون به هناك.
It took as long as the Taj Mahal.
لقد استغرق بناؤه ما استغرقه تاج محل.
Unfortunately it took so long that Lou never saw it finished.
و للأسف استغرق بناؤه طويلاً لدرجة أن والدي "لو" لم يشهد انتهاء بنائه.
He died in 1974.
فقد توفي عام 1974
The building was finished in 1983.
و انتهى بناء المبنى عام 1983
So it continued on for many years
أي استمر بناؤه عدة سنوات
after he died.
بعد وفاته
Think about that when you see that building,
أود منكم أن تفكروا خلال مشاهدة الفلم
that sometimes the things we strive for so hard in life we never get to see finished.
أن الأشياء التي نسعى جاهدين لإنجازها خلال حياتنا، لا يكتب لنا أنا نراها منتهية.
And that really struck me about my father,
و هذا ما صدمني حول والدي،
in the sense that he had such belief
بمعنى أنه كان مؤمناً بشدة
that somehow, doing these things
بأنه و بطريقة ما و من خلال قيامه بهذه الأشياء
giving in the way that he gave, that something good would come out of it,
و من خلال التضحيات التي قام بها، بأنه سيرى ثمار هذا الجهد و التضحيات
even in the middle of a war, there was a war with Pakistan at one point,
و حتى خلال الحرب التي جرت مع باكستان في احدى المراحل،
and the construction stopped totally and he kept working,
و بالرغم من أن البناء توقف تماماً استمر هو في العمل،
because he felt, "Well when the war is done
لأنه كان يقول في نفسه "حسناً، عندما تنتهي الحرب
they'll need this building."
سيكونون بحاجة لهذا المبنى"
So, those are the two clips I'm going to show.
و هذان هما المقطعان اللذان سأعرضهما.
Roll that tape.
ابدأ العرض.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Richard Saul Wurman: I remember hearing him talk at Penn.
ريتشارد سول ورمان: أذكر سماعي له يتحدث في ولاية بنسلفانيا
And I came home and I said to my father and mother,
و عدت إلى المنزل و قلت لأمي و أبي:
"I just met this man: doesn't have much work,
"التقيت لتوي رجلاً، ليس لديه الكثير من العمل"
and he's sort of ugly, funny voice,
"و هو قبيح إلى حد ما و وجهه مضحك"
and he's a teacher at school.
" و هو مدرس في المدرسة"
I know you've never heard of him, but just mark this day
" أعلم أنكم لم تسمعوا به يوماً و لكن اذكروا هذا اليوم"
that someday you will hear of him,
" لأنكم ستسمعون به يوماً ما"
because he's really an amazing man."
" لأنه حقاً رجل رائع"
Frank Gehry: I heard he had some kind of a fling with Ingrid Bergman. Is that true?
فرانك غيري: سمعت بأنه كان على علاقة مع إنغريد بيرغمن، فهل ذلك صحيح؟
Nathaniel Kahn: If he did he was a very lucky man.
نثانيال خان: إن كان ذلك صحيحا فهو رجل محظوظ جداً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
NK: Did you hear that, really?
هل سمعت ذلك حقاً؟
FG: Yeah, when he was in Rome.
نعم، عندما كان في روما.
Moshe Safdie: He was a real nomad.
موشيه سافدي: لقد كان رجلاً كثير التجوال بحق.
And you know, when I knew him when I was in the office,
و عندما عرفته حين كنت أعمل معه في المكتب
he would come in from a trip, and he would be in the office
كان ليعود من إحدى رحلاته، و يبقى مدة طويلة في المكتب
for two or three days intensely, and he would pack up and go.
ليومين أو ثلاثة بشكل شبه متواصل، ثم يقوم بحزم أغراضه و يذهب من جديد.
You know he'd be in the office till three in the morning working with us
كان كثيراً ما يبقى في المكتب حتى الثالثة صباحاً يعمل معنا
and there was this kind of sense of the nomad in him.
و كنت لتحس بأنه من النوع المحب للتجوال.
I mean as tragic as his death was in a railway station,
و بالرغم من الطريقة المأساوية التي توفي بيها في محطة قطار
it was so consistent with his life, you know?
كانت وفاته متناسقة مع نمط حياته.
I mean I often think I'm going to die in a plane,
أعني بأني غالباً ما أعتقد بأني سأموت في طائرة،
or I'm going to die in an airport,
أو في مطار،
or die jogging without an identification on me.
أو أموت و أنا أجري دون أن يكون معي بطاقة تعريف.
I don't know why I sort of carry that
لا أدري لماذا أحمل هذا النوع من الأفكار
from that memory of the way he died.
منذ اليوم و الطريقة التي توفي بها.
But he was a sort of a nomad at heart.
و لكنه كان محباً للترحال في أعماقه.
Louis Kahn: How accidental our existences are really
لويس خان: كم هو عرضيٌ وجودنا
and how full of influence by circumstance.
و إلى أي درجة يتأثر بالعوامل والظروف المحيطة.
Man: We are the morning workers who come, all the time, here
نحن العمال الصباحيون، كنا نأتي هنا طوال الوقت
and enjoy the walking, city's beauty and the atmosphere
و نستمتع بالسير و بجمال المدينة و بالجو العام
and this is the nicest place of Bangladesh.
و هذا المكان هو أجمل الأماكن في بنغلاديش.
We are proud of it.
نحن فخورون به.
NK: You're proud of it?
نثانيال خان: أنتم فخورون به؟
Man: Yes, it is the national image of Bangladesh.
نعم، إنه الصورة القومية لبنغلاديش.
NK: Do you know anything about the architect?
نثانيال خان: هل تعلم أي شيء عن المعماري الذي صممه؟
Man: Architect? I've heard about him; he's a top-ranking architect.
معماري؟ سمعت أنه كان معماري جيد.
NK: Well actually I'm here because I'm the architect's son,
نثانيال خان: في الواقع أنا هنا لأنني ابن هذا المعماري.
he was my father.
إنه والدي.
Man: Oh! Dad is Louis Farrakhan?
حقاً ! والدك هو لويس فاراخان؟
NK: Yeah. No not Louis Farrakhan, Louis Kahn.
نثانيال خان: نعم. ليس لويس فاراخان، بل لويس خان.
Man: Louis Kahn, yes!
لويس خان، أجل!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Man: Your father, is he alive?
هل ما يزال والدك حياً؟
NK: No, he's been dead for 25 years.
لا، لقد توفي منذ 25 عاماً.
Man: Very pleased to welcome you back.
يسرني أن أرحب بعودتك.
NK: Thank you.
شكراً لك.
NK: He never saw it finished, Pop.
لم يشهد اكتمال هذا المبنى.
No, he never saw this.
لم يره منتهياً.
Shamsul Wares: It was almost impossible, building for a country like ours.
سامويل ووريس: كان من المستحيل تقريباً البناء لبلد كبلدنا.
In 30, 50 years back, it was nothing, only paddy fields,
منذ 50 عاماً لم يكن لدينا شيء تقريباً سوى الحقول المستوية.
and since we invited him here,
و منذ أن دعيناه إلى هنا
he felt that he has got a responsibility.
لقد شعر بأن عليه مسؤولية.
He wanted to be a Moses here, he gave us democracy.
أراد أن يكون منقذاً هنا، لقد أعطانا ديمقراطيةً.
He is not a political man,
إنه ليس رجلاً سياسياً،
but in this guise he has given us
و لكنه بهذا الرداء أعطانا
the institution for democracy, from where we can rise.
مؤسسة للديمقراطية في بلدنا، و من هنا نستطيع أن ننمو و نتطور.
In that way it is so relevant.
من هذه الناحية نرى علاقة قوية.
He didn't care for how much money this country has,
لم يهتم لغنى هذا البلد
or whether he would be able to ever finish this building,
أو لفكرة أنه قد لا يستطيع انهاء هذا المبنى أبداً
but somehow he has been able to do it, build it, here.
و لكنه و بطريقة ما استطاع أن يبنيه هنا.
And this is the largest project he has got in here, the poorest country in the world.
و هذا هو أكبر مشروع حصل عليه، و في أفقر بلد في العالم.
NK: It cost him his life.
نثانيال خان: و كلفه هذا حياته.
SW: Yeah, he paid. He paid his life for this,
نعم لقد دفع حياته ثمناً له.
and that is why he is great and we'll remember him.
و لذلك فهو عظيم و نحن جميعاً نذكره.
But he was also human.
و لكنه كان أيضاً إنسانياً
Now his failure to satisfy the family life,
و الآن فشله لإرضاء حياة العائلة
is an inevitable association of great people.
هو ما يضعه حتماً في صف الناس العظماء
But I think his son will understand this,
و لكني أعتقد بأن ابنه سيتفهم ذلك
and will have no sense of grudge,
و لن يكون لديه أي شعور بالحسد أو الضغينة
or sense of being neglected, I think.
أو إحساس بالإهمال
He cared in a very different manner,
لقد اهتم بعائلته بطريقة مختلفة
but it takes a lot of time to understand that.
و لكن تفهم هذه الطريقة تتطلب الكثير من الوقت.
In social aspect of his life
و من ناحية حياته الاجتماعية
he was just like a child, he was not at all matured.
كان أشبه بطفل لم ينضج أبداً.
He could not say no to anything,
لم يكن يستطيع أن يرفض أي شيء
and that is why, that he cannot say no to things,
و لهذا السبب
we got this building today.
لدينا هذا البناء اليوم.
You see, only that way you can be able to understand him.
و بهذه الطريقة فقط تستطيعون تفهمه
There is no other shortcut,
ليس هناك أي اختصارات أو طرق أخرى
no other way to really understand him.
ليس هناك طريقة أخرى لتفهمه
But I think he has given us this building
و لكني أؤمن بأنه منحنا هذا البناء
and we feel all the time for him,
و نحن نشعر بالإمتنان الدائم له
that's why, he has given love for us.
و بهذا كان قد منحنا الحب.
He could not probably give the right kind of love for you,
أعتقد أنه لم يمنحك الشكل الصحيح من الحب
but for us, he has given the people the right kind of love,
و لكنه أعطانا نحن النوع الصحيح من الحب و التعاطف
that is important.
و هذا شيء مهم.
You have to understand that.
عليك أن تتفهم ذلك.
He had an enormous amount of love,
كان لديه مقدار كبير من الحب
he loved everybody.
أحب الجميع
To love everybody, he sometimes did not see
و ليفعل ذلك، كان في بعض الأحيان لا يرى
the very closest ones,
أقرب الناس إليه
and that is inevitable for men of his stature.
و هذا شيء حتمي لرجال من نوعه
(Applause)
(تصفيق)